[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
support for this episode comes from
single store scaling modern sas is hard
it's even harder when you're using
databases that were built the last time
boy bands and low rise jeans were all
the rage single store is a modern cloud
database built for today's data
intensive applications and the smart sas
generation single store power is the new
wave of sas technologies displacing
legacy providers used to break the data
bottleneck and reduce your monthly cloud
bill in the process
learn how single store can help you at
singlestore.com
se radio
this is philip winston for software
engineering radio my guest today is
audrey lawrence audrey is a software
development manager at amazon her focus
there is on their new database service
which is called amazon timestream
audrey has worked in the software
industry for more than 10 years at
companies such as microsoft uber cruise
automation and carmara as a disclosure i
first met audrey when we were both
working at carmera a few years ago
let's start at the top
what is a time series database
a time series database is a database
that is purpose built for time series
data and when we're talking about time
series data what we're talking about
really is data points that are measured
over time
so this is useful when you're measuring
events that change over time so when
you're not just interested in the
current measurement for some metric but
you really want to look at
the measurements over a period of time
and you see this commonly in a number of
industries and actually this is also a
really fast growing data storage type
that we see across industries
and what time series databases do
are they allow for really efficient
collection storage and analysis on top
of this data so everything from doing
streaming analytics in real time to
maybe training machine learning models
off of historical time series data
and these databases really allow for
some complex analyses as well that you
do on top of time series data
and what amazon time stream is is it is
one of these purpose-built databases for
time series data
okay so i know the financial industry
has long used produced time series data
they have data going back over 100 years
on
stock prices
so to get specific what other
applications or industries tend to
produce time series data
yeah finance is definitely one very
common example that you hear for time
series data so looking at stock prices
over time or different prices of
commodities
and another big area that we see a lot
of time series data is in the systems
monitoring use case so a lot of
developers now and engineers
want observability into their
applications and their infrastructure to
have really granular metrics about the
performance and to ensure that things
are running well and systems are healthy
so you see a lot of times developers
will add
metrics to monitor different latencies
of components different response codes
that type of thing
and actually one of time stream's
biggest customers is a video streaming
service and they use timestream for this
use case to monitor their video
streaming content so collecting metrics
like
frame rate drops latencies that type of
thing so that they can ensure really
high
quality content streaming to their
customers and
you know this this use case also you get
a lot of data at times we can see up to
you know gigabytes per second of
ingestion
and really up to millions of queries per
hour another big area where we see time
series data is with the internet of
things the iot space both in industrial
settings and then also commercial
settings there's a move to kind of
instrument everything and create smart
devices
and these collect a lot of telemetry of
the world around them so thinking like
heart smart home sensors your smart
thermostat that's measuring temperature
air quality those type of metrics over
time one
that i've gotten really used to is a
smartwatch that i initially got as an
upgrade from my 10 stopwatch for running
to measure pace while i'm out running
but since i've gotten it i've become
really accustomed to all of the metrics
it's collecting at all times things like
heart rate heart rate variability
air pressure that type of thing
and we'll see this area grow as we start
to make everything smarter
yeah that makes a lot of sense and for
monitoring the data center i can imagine
there's thousands of
machines and and many more metrics and
for consumer devices there could be
millions of of devices so i can see how
the
scale is going to add up so i think
anytime there's a new type of database
one question that comes to mind is
why can't developers store time series
data in a sql database or a key value
store
or some type of database that already
has existed for a long period of time
what limitations or problems might they
experience if they did
use a sql database they
yeah so developers certainly can use
more conventional databases to sort time
series data i've
done this before in the past as well
but the problems that you tend to run
into are around really scaling those
systems out for
performance and costs
given time series databases
just are purpose-built for this type of
data they can do a more efficient job in
ingesting storing and querying the data
another area too that kind of gets teams
to adopt time series databases is the
tooling around these data stores there
are a lot of different
plugins you can use to really easily
collect and ingest these metrics and
then also visualization tools that help
later with
querying and that type of thing
and then another piece too
that kind of
moves
teams to look into using time series
databases are just the the solutions
that they may need to come up with to in
order to store time series databases can
get rather complex and can take a lot of
developer time to build and then to
maintain and scale out these systems um
there is a recent
all things distributed blog post by
amazon cto that discussed this a bit and
referred to these systems or compared
them to rube goldberg machines
where we've seen
teams manage their time series databases
with really complex architectures
where they need some system that can
essentially like cue the data coming in
store it in some sort of durable store
have some massive parallel processing
framework that process that data and
stores it in an optimized format for
querying and these solutions are pretty
difficult to build and maintain and
really scale and a lot of times the
metrics that you're storing in these
stores are also your
really critical business or operational
metrics which need to be timely and
correct so
moving to a solution that can
solve a lot of these problems for you
and also if it can do it in a
more performant and cost effective
manner
means that you'll see
it may just be the right choice for your
team
yeah that makes sense that you could
start out with a sql database for a
smaller implementation but you're going
to run into trouble with scale and and
and other factors
let me take a minute to list some
relevant past episodes of software
engineering radio this is the first
episode we've done on time series
databases but many past episodes have
dealt with other types of databases
these are just a few episode 102
relational databases
episode 165 nosql and mongodb with
dwight merriman
episode 194 michael hunger on graph
databases
episode 417 alex petrov on database
storage engines and i will put links to
these episodes and the blog posts you
mentioned in the show notes
so
let's dive in let's start with data
modeling
how does someone create a data model for
a time series database and how is this
different from
modeling for a sql database
when you're using a time series database
the core unit that you really care about
are
what we call records and this is just a
single measurement of a metric at a
point in time
and a series of these measurements over
time is what makes up the time series
and for each of these time series you
have a group of attributes or dimensions
that kind of describe that time series
and then those you can store in
databases and tables to organize the
data and control access retention and
that type of thing
so an example of this would be if we are
monitoring a fleet of hosts in our
system we could have a
devops database and maybe a host metrics
table
and then the dimensions that we would
want to store with our time series to
describe the different time series would
be things like region where that fleet
is located
host name for the different hosts os
version different things like that and
then the measurements that we are the
actual metrics we're collecting so
things like cpu utilization
memory utilization and traffic work
traffic io that those type of
measurements
so those are the main concepts that you
would think about when
ingesting into a time series database
and based on your use case kind of model
what business metrics you're collecting
um into that type of format which most
you know time series as you're thinking
about can really fit well into that
and time series databases also have tend
to have really flexible schema so for
time stream you don't
outside of creating a database in a
table you don't
declare
your measurements and dimensions up
front but you could declare them when
you're ingesting data and time stream
will kind of figure that out and store
the data appropriately
whereas if you were
using a sql store to store your time
series data typically what you see here
and you do see this a lot i've done this
a lot in my past as well
it's pretty convenient to do this
especially if you have other data
already in your sql data store that you
would want to join with
then it makes it a lot easier to have
your time series data also in that store
and what you typically have is um
tables with one row per measurement so
each of these attributes would also be
you know in a kind of denormalized view
in that row and so you can kind of see
that these dimension values would be
repeated for each measurement which that
can grow
costly because you're storing a lot more
data in that case
and then also you have to read through
that
data when you're doing queries typically
you see here that you'll add an index on
the for the time column
and you'll probably also want to add
other indices too on some of the
dimensions so that you can have query
pro
so that you can query based on those
dimensions this also gets a little bit
hard to balance because you don't want
to add too many indices you kind of have
bloated indexes and then on ingestion
that will cost a lot
but also
you do need to leverage these indices um
at query time or sometimes the queries
can just get way too slow
and then the one of the other problems
that you can run into using a
conventional store here is kind of the
nature of time series data is to
grow over time as time moves on you
continuously collect more and more
measurements so what you see here people
tend to partition by time so partition
their tables based on time
and
then that helps you know tables not grow
too long you can kind of prune those
tables over time
these solutions are um
still really hard to get right um you
have to do a lot of tuning of the
indices and how you're doing
partitioning
so it's a bit simpler to use a
purpose-built store that handles this
type of data for you
you can also see too
using a column-oriented format where
you'll store kind of all the data points
for measurements in one column and then
you can kind of query just for that
column at a time but you still run into
a number of challenges too of how you
partition the data in an efficient
manner
okay so one of the things i read said
that time stream partitions data by
space as well as time was that physical
like geographic space because you
mentioned regions or is it something
more abstract
it's a bit more abstract
so to go back to why you would want to
partition data you have partitioned data
essentially in data stores in order to
scale ingestion storage and query
and typically what we we see for time
series data that
you would want to partition based on
time because this allows you to kind of
have more parallelized
reads and also your
the queries all tend to be around the
time element so it makes sense to be
able to quickly determine what data
points are relevant to serve your query
and you know just have the query engine
read those partitions
but
as
for most time series that we see there
are exceptions to this but a lot of
times the data that you're ingesting is
at or around current time
and so
indexing
or partitioning just by time isn't
really sufficient to distribute the
ingestion traffic
across your your fleet if you're seeing
a lot of ingestion throughput to a table
and then also too at query time you do
want to be able to also kind of scale
out queries so multiple workers can read
multiple partitions if you are
serving a query that has a kind of
longer
temporal window
so
you want to
partition as well
by some other attributes and how you can
you use the dimensions and the
attributes on those time series to
determine how to organize the data
so how time stream does this is what we
call partitioning by space and time and
the way to
best kind of understand this is to
picture a
2d grid in which all of the data points
for
your table will live and along the
x-axis is your time axis or axis and
then the y-axis would be what we call
the spatial dimension and for all of the
time series that you have in that table
would
consist of
you know dots that go in horizontal
lines so the horizontal line would
represent one time series and there
would be a data point at the time
point in which the measurement is taken
and how we want to organize the
different horizontal lines or time
series are just by similarity so storing
all of the you know data points similar
in time for one time series together and
then also storing
similar series close together because
those are more likely to be
queried together
and then kind of when we um do our
partitioning we will kind of cut
this grid into
other 2d boxes and store you know those
as partitions so that we can really
quickly you know look up in our kind of
2d index to figure out where the data is
located and then when we're doing
reads we're pulling
hopefully just the
data that we need to serve that query
and don't have to do a lot of pruning
after we get the data points from that
partition
okay i think we're straddling data
modeling and ingestion so let's dive
into ingestion some more
at the beginning we mentioned consumer
devices i imagine ingestion
is different depending on the number of
sources being ingested so maybe it's one
data center that's putting out a lot of
metrics or maybe it's a million consumer
devices how does ingestion process
differ or what are the challenges of
these two extremes
so yeah there's definitely two types of
cases where that you see for time series
data where you can have you know
millions of iot devices out there all
sending metrics to the same
table and then also the the case where
you have a really high rate
per device of time series data being
produced and this i i
familiar with the latter case of my time
before amazon working in the
self-driving car industry because you
really see a lot of these um in the
robotics industry
with maybe really high frequency sensors
that are collecting a lot of data
really high
volumes of data being produced at one
point we're collecting
hundreds of megabytes per second per car
so ingesting all of that you need to be
able to handle large batches of data
coming in
the case the former case is
really tricky as well because
you um
have
um really high throughput of data and
they're um
you you need to have
large ingestion fleets that can handle
traffic from many devices and also
ensure that you're not having a lot of
fan out afterwards into your storage
layer
so how we kind of handle this is with um
our
ingestion auto scaling so we use these
kind of 2d partitions that we just
talked about
and how
we determine how we
slice them further and do further
partitioning based on the ingestion
throughput that we're seeing at any
given time to a table so for instance if
we're seeing
so i guess first for terminology we
refer to any of these partitions as
tiles so i may be
using that word a bit
but if we see a lot of ingestion pick up
to one tile and we see that the
resources that are
we may be constrained in the resources
that are able to accept that ingestion
throughput what we'll do is we'll again
split that tile into two tiles that can
serve
essentially twice as much throughput
and we'll continue doing that
over time to kind of distribute our
ingestion traffic so that we can still
serve these really high
throughput use cases
okay
you mentioned the frequency of data
coming from these self-driving cars
what sort of frequencies are common in
time series databases for example high
frequency trading operates at the scale
of milliseconds what frequencies do you
typically see
it definitely varies by the use case um
we see sometimes even the need for
nanosecond precision and that's what we
support in time stream is up to
nanosecond it really um depends on the
use case sometimes we
we see use cases where maybe you only
have a metric per hour or even per day
and
that we certainly support but some of
these really high frequency and where
you need that sort of time precision use
cases maybe even like the monitoring use
case too where
you have systems that are really low
latency themselves and are producing
metrics at faster than at the
millisecond level so we do support
nanoseconds
okay this might be straddling the topic
of ingestion and queries but
once data is ingested how quickly
does it need to be queryable or how
quickly can it be queryable
and just what challenges are there and
making the data available as fast as
possible
for many use cases you want the
recently ingested data to be available
in under a second there are a number of
different
customer use cases out there where
that are very time sensitive such as if
the monitoring use case if you're
monitoring your ecommerce site on black
friday or cyber monday i guess it is you
um want to know if there are any issues
immediately because you could be losing
um
hundreds of thousands of dollars
millions of dollars per second that your
site is down also other
real-time analytics use cases or say if
you're doing fraud detection
on different purchases you want the
latest data to be
serving these predictions you don't want
data from an hour ago you don't even
want data from five minutes ago so
getting the data um ingested and
queryable is really
and doing that quickly is really
important
and there are a lot of challenges with
doing this the same kind of with any
distributed data system where you um
with the
top priority of any
data system is durability so you need to
ensure once you ingest that data that it
is correct and durable
and so you'll want to you know have
redundancy in your system system so
you're storing
replicated copies of that data and
ensuring it's consistent when customers
go to read that data
and how we do this for time stream is we
have all of our ingestion coming into a
fault tolerant memory store
so a single kind of writer node will
accept rights and then we will
replicate that out across three
different availability zones and have
you know quorum base consensus so that
we can handle a node going down or an
entire availability zone going down
and then that allows us kind of
serving this the ingest traffic in
memory to um
be really fast with how we are able to
ingest the data and then make it
instantaneously queryable
support for this episode comes from
single store the single database for all
data intensive applications why make the
switch scaling modern sas is already
hard it's even harder when you're using
databases that were built back when all
your friends had pet rocks and the most
stressful part of your day was
connecting to the dial-up modem single
store is built for the smart sas
generation and all the data intensive
applications that come with it the
single store cloud powers the new wave
of sas technologies displacing legacy
providers with insights for apps
effortless operation of models at scale
and easy shifts to the cloud introduce
simplicity and ease to your data
structure and watch what happens to your
speed scale and sql
find out why industry leaders trust
single store to modernize their data
platforms see for yourself at
singlestore.com
try dash free
so scale is obviously an important topic
here
can you describe
what difficulties does scale present to
the ingestion process let's suppose we
have many data sources and they are all
high volume so the total amount of data
being ingested is huge how can you cope
with that
yeah so we we have seen some use cases
with time stream where we see really
massive amounts of data coming in at one
time so workloads where we see you know
gigabytes per second per table coming in
and you can't really handle that volume
of data without distributing the load in
some fashion
and
how we do this is we distribute the load
by cutting
more into our two-dimensional space of
tiles
so in order to
really increase if we're seeing a lot of
increased traffic to these tiles and we
will further split them down so that we
can
have more resources working on ingestion
for that table and then similarly if we
see workload decrease to the table then
we can merge tiles back together so that
we don't have resources not working on a
lot of
incoming data
and
yeah
by
nature time series data is also
somewhat interesting to verse other data
that you see like in online cases
because most of the time time series
data is
immutable and also coming in order at or
around current time there are a lot of
times when this is not the case so we do
need to support
you know data updates and data
deduplication if we are receiving
duplicate data points
and then also supporting out-of-order
data or even data that could be really
old but a lot of times time series data
does come in in this fashion
so that allows us to really scale our
system and
not have a lot of you know conflicts
when multiple different hosts are kind
of getting the exact same data points
they need to ingest but we do
have to deal with this case and we do
have a matter of doing kind of batching
and load balancing with our ingestion
service
so i think you hear you saying that it's
not just the volume of data it's the
dynamic range that you have to be able
to support the amount of data
becoming more or less as it proceeds
yeah that's true for
systems that are such as timeshare where
we don't know up front what workloads to
expect from customers that it can really
be dynamic and we want to ensure that
we're being cost effective in the
resources that we're using and also can
scale up really really quickly to
support any fluctuations and workloads
from customers
okay i want to talk a little bit about
lifecycle management when i was reading
about time series database i found it
interesting that many times customers
choose to age out their data
is this strictly because of storage
costs or are there other reasons
um typically you see this is due to
storage costs and
the fact that you may not have a
business use case for the older data
so
the nature of time series data is to
continually grow as time moves forward
and you're collecting more and more
measurements and sometimes
the the older data that you have could
be larger volume and expensive to store
and if you don't need to query it then
it can make sense to age out of your
system
also sometimes you see that
the raw data measurements that you're
ingesting can sometimes be really high
in volume
and these can be you know expensive to
store all of the raw data and then also
expensive to repeatably scan all of that
data at query time if you're doing some
of the same queries over time so you see
use cases where instead of storing all
of the raw data for a long period of
time you um run queries on kind of roll
ups of that data and store those
aggregations somewhere that has a longer
retention and then have a shorter
retention on the raw data
so that being said are there use cases
where 100 of the data is kept
indefinitely
yes there are certainly use cases where
you would want to keep the data forever
thinking the medical industry or
financial industry where you may have
legal or compliance reasons to keep the
data indefinitely
and then also the data could be really
useful
i think a lot of times time series data
could be used when you're training an ml
model and a lot of times you'll want as
much data or as many unique events as
possible to for training data and then
sometimes to
if if you have like rare events in that
historical data sample so maybe if
you're training a weather forecasting
model and have some like really rare
weather events you'll want to
keep that data for longer i remember
one time working in self-driving car
industry and the power went out in san
francisco and we really wanted to ensure
that we retained all of the data we
collected during that time in which all
of the traffic lights were down in the
entire city so cases like that i think
those exist
that makes sense that different
industries have different uh compliance
or
business use cases so i read about hot
data versus cold data does hot data mean
it's stored in ram and cold data mean
it's on disk or is it not always that
straightforward
typically with time series when you're
talking about hot data you're talking
about the online use case where you're
doing
real-time analysis on the latest data or
monitoring of the latest data so for for
that it's the latest data so this is the
data that's just been written you need
really fast rights and then also
you want these queries to be really fast
returning in milliseconds um so to get
this type of performance where you have
really fast rights and really fast reads
i think typically you would store the
data in memory in that use case
and then
this is more expensive to store data
here versus storing the data on disk so
then i think that that's why
you would typically want to push the
older more historical data that
is serving a lot of the offline use
cases onto disk at that time so kind of
your cold data on disk and this data can
kind of cover larger time periods the
needs for querying aren't as low latency
as the online use case and then kind of
storing in a read optimized format since
you're typically serving more reads off
of this data
and time stream manages this with two
different data stores that have two
different retention periods so time
stream has two tiers for storage one we
call the memory store and this store you
know stores the data in memory most
recent data and then we have a magnetic
store which stores the data on disk so
when a customer is setting up their
table for their time series data they
declare the retention periods for the
memory store and retention periods for
the magnetic store
and then the
time stream itself takes care of moving
the data around querying between the two
layers and
this is all pretty transparent to the
user other than the memory store will
have
faster query performance
and that will cost a bit more for
storage as well
so you mentioned the real-time analysis
of recent data what is the relationship
between time series databases and
visualization tools like grafana
what do you see customers using with
their time series database
yeah i think it's very natural for us
when we're thinking about time series
data to think in terms of how to
visualize that data even thinking of our
example of financial data and you're
probably thinking of like the stock
track tracker where you can very easily
visualize with a line on a graph of the
stock price plotted over time of it
rising or decreasing or crazy spikes
and that type of thing so that's very
common for all sorts of time series data
and having tools like grafana to
visualize this are really really useful
um especially when in the case where
you're
monitoring or building reports for your
data so for the
operational metrics when you're
monitoring a system grafana's common
tools you use here and other tools like
it where you can easily create a
dashboard that allows you to have a lot
of aggregate metrics over time
and this uh the the query language for
these is really natural for time series
data where you can
you know do these aggregate percentiles
or averages
do groupings by
different dimensions doing
roll-ups by minutes or hours or day they
auto-refresh
they're much easier to
use versus maybe like handcrafting sql
and sending sql queries against the data
store
or looking at the raw time series data
itself and there are also a number of
business intelligence tools as well that
you can use for reporting or doing
analysis on
against time series databases time
stream has integration with amazon
quicksite and a number of other tools
and we we do support a sql query
interface with a lot of extra
time series specific functions and have
support for jdbc drivers so a number of
different vi tools you can hook up to
query your time stream data
so when we're talking about querying
recent data or live data what type of
query performance do people expect
compared to say doing a report on the
historical data
so for querying live data you would
expect um query responses in
milliseconds and for these you know
you're querying typically
maybe tens of gigabytes or fewer data
points um and so
this is the data that you typically have
stored in memory that can really quickly
serve these data
or these data queries
also for this use case you tend to see a
lot of concurrent queries as well so
thinking of your if you have a grafana
dashboard that's monitoring your system
there that each time it refreshes every
minute or so maybe sending you know tens
or hundreds of queries to the data store
that you want returned
immediately almost
and then when you're doing kind of more
ad hoc analytical queries or maybe
fetching data for ml training
you can you can scan a lot more data so
you can scan terabytes or even petabytes
of data and the latency requirements
aren't as
strict here seconds is acceptable
and how we handle those with timestream
too is having an adaptive distributed
query engine that will like
auto scale based on
the type of query that we see coming in
so it does some estimation on how
complex is the query and how much data
how many of these 2d tiles is the query
going to need to
fetch and then it can distribute that
load off out of a fleet of workers so
what we've seen kind of benchmarking
this is as the amount of data that we
see as the datum volume that we query
grows the query latencies themselves
don't grow nearly as fast
we've been talking about performance
this whole time but let's dig even
deeper
i can imagine that
ingestion performance and query
performance are very different things
which matters most or how do you balance
providing these two things
so what we see for a lot of time series
use cases are that both really matter
both ingestion and
query performance tend to matter and you
can see this with a number of different
use cases so
suppose we we have some real time and
analytics use case or say we're doing
fraud detection on incoming data and
for that we we need both the ability to
act upon the latest data so rights to be
really efficient and then also reads to
be really fast so that we can make our
predictions very fast we've seen this
too with the
video streaming
service that uses time stream for
monitoring where if they are about to
release maybe a new tv show is about to
come out they'll expect a lot more users
to be watching that
at the time that it's released and that
will produce a lot more
data for monitoring and then also those
are kind of the critical times for their
service to be up and running so if what
you tend to see in
many of these use cases is that both
really matter for performance and
that's one of the things for time stream
where we've
built the system so that we can scale
both of those separately and also
benchmarked really high
loads for both write and read together
to kind of test out these real world
cases
yeah i read you need to be able to scale
ingestion query and even storage
separately is this to support different
customer types or is one customer going
to
need these different things over their
lifetime
it depends i think having having the
ability to scale separately
allows us to
you know dynamically respond to
what um workloads we're seeing both for
ingestion query and storage
there there are
use cases where you may see both heavy
ingesting query that we just talked
about but there are also use cases where
maybe you are just having you know heavy
volumes of queries so i'm thinking if
you if you have a use case where you're
doing a lot of training of ml models or
really heavy analysis against the
historical data so you'll want to be
able to still independently
scale your system to support those
workloads
okay we talked about storing data in ram
or disk how specifically does the
developer configure where that split
should happen is it just a question of
time like all data that's older than
one day is stored in on disk or is it
more complicated
it's typically a matter of time when
we're looking at the the table level um
that's how time stream manages that is
that
with the
developer setting up the table will
set a memory retention period and a
magnetic retention period and when data
is older than the memory retention we'll
each that data to the magnetic store
and this these values are
just time durations so typically based
on the the use case you'll set maybe a
day or
30 days or maybe even a year for your in
memory store and then that will be kind
of a sliding window from now that will
age out data older
than that period and this this is
kind of where
it varies a lot based on the the
customer use case of how you're using
this data and what the query patterns
are and
what we see is that if you if you do
have multiple
use cases then a lot of times naturally
those time series will fall into maybe
two different tables and you could have
different retention settings for those
tables
okay we talked about sql databases early
on and how they're likely not going to
scale with a large time series
application
but what specifically about queries is
faster with the time series database
compared to sql
yeah so what's faster than conventional
databases um is how the data tends to be
stored so what time series databases do
is really optimizing how
they store data so such as you know
storing all of the data points for one
series together and then storing the
similar series together so that when
you're serving a query you're
able to just read the um
data that's relevant to cert for your
query um and then really efficiently
indexing this data as well
so that you you can quickly um
you know
we have a 2d
indexing that maps into kind of our 2d
time and space
grid where we store all of the data
points
so what we want to do when queries come
in is really efficiently be able to look
up where the data is
and then you know quickly prune out the
the tiles that aren't relevant to serve
that query and then have kind of the
minimum amount of non-relevant data
points in the tiles that we do serve
back
and then also another
kind of
the query engines too this is probably
coming with conventional databases as
well
but being able to really distribute
queries um is also really important to
keep
query performance
good as the data set grows because with
the time series use case we know for a
fact that as time goes on we'll continue
growing and growing that data set so
being able to massively scale out data
queries over time is also really
important
so moving on from performance amazon
timestream is a serverless database
what advantage does a serverless
implementation have for the user
yeah so one big benefit of serverless
and this somewhat goes into performance
and auto scaling is that
the user of a serverless data store
doesn't have to think too much about
what type of load they need to support
in advance so
there's there's no resources that they
need to provision so they don't have to
think in advance
you know how many nodes does my data
store need to be on what type of
instance type do i need to
have you know good performance to serve
the ingestion and read traffic for this
data store and they don't need to manage
scaling up when they see
you know increased usage of the time
series store um nor worry about scaling
down when they you know see
less usage and don't want to pay for
being over provisioned so this is this
is really helpful
for users of
databases just to not have to manage the
instances themselves and scaling those
up and down
you only pay for what you use which is
nice and
i think this is really helpful
especially for different data teams at
companies because it's really hard for
time series data to do upfront capacity
estimation thinking you know you have to
work with all of the different teams at
your company to understand what their
time series usage is and then kind of
plan ahead for what their ingestion
volume will be what their storage will
be over time and then also how they
expect to query that data and that
that's hard to do in an accurate manner
so it's then hard to ensure that you um
you know have the capacity that you need
and that you're not paying to be over
provisioned
i've seen this before working on data
teams too that
it's it's really difficult to get
accurate estimates especially if teams
aren't yet um using the solution so
being serverless really helps with this
paying for what you use and then also it
helps with just the operational load
where you're not managing the
resources themselves so a lot of times
managing databases is you know
non-trivial amount of work where you
have to keep it on the latest patches
you have to make sure it's highly
available these are difficult
operational tests
yes i guess again we're talking about
the dynamic range of how much data the
company or the user is processing and i
can see if that varies a lot that
serverless is going to be potentially
easier to manage
i read that time stream is cell based is
that the same as tiles or is that
something else related to architecture
that's something else that's related
more to the architecture and the
infrastructure that time stream runs on
so this is a pattern that is used at aws
i think aurora uses this as well but how
we've architected time stream itself is
to
run as a full system
in multiple
isolated what we call cells so the
system itself is segmented into multiple
copies of itself and customer traffic
coming in will just go to one of these
copies so what this allows is each of
these um
cells runs in an isolated fashion so if
there is a
an incident in one of the cells then it
won't impact any of the other cells and
why we do this is it
you know in the case that there is an
incident this really dramatically
reduces the blast radius
we haven't mentioned security at all how
does a serverless design impact security
considerations
yeah so a serverless design can help
with the customer of a type of a
database and not have to worry as much
about the different security
implications since they're not managing
the resources themselves they're not
managing the instances or the storage
nodes they don't have to
ensure that those are secure running the
latest software managing access to them
the data store manages you know all
security at kind of the top level so for
time stream for
secure by default we encrypt data both
in transit and at rest by default
and customers can they can you bring a
key to encrypt the data with them or
they can just leave that completely to
time stream to manage so this really
makes security i think a lot more simple
for customers
than being serverless
great
okay let's start wrapping up what are
some trends that you have noticed in
time series databases where do you see
things evolving in the next three to
five years
i think where we'll see a lot of
evolution in time series databases is
just their growth and adoption i think
right now we're just getting started in
terms of usage of time series databases
and the functionality that they can
serve and if you think about it so
much data out there across so many
industries this time series in nature
and you know most data that you're
collecting
has some sort of time element that you
tend to not so much care about
the current state of things but you want
historical data as well and especially
as machine learning expands and we make
you know devices and different operators
smarter and smarter
kind of giving them insight into this
historical data as well is really
important and i think another area that
we'll see is as
time series databases become more
are more well used that we'll see more
use cases erupting right now
as well across different industries so i
think that's really an exciting area to
see
what all will be using time series
databases in the future
yeah i can see adoption being a
something that's going to
accelerate
is there anything we missed that you'd
like to mention
one thing we didn't talk a lot about was
just the types of queries that you
typically see and the types of analysis
that you do on the time series data and
i think that's a really interesting area
so to talk a little bit about
what types of queries you would
run on time series data a lot of times
what you're doing is doing aggregates
over time or maybe filtering by some of
those dimension attributes so if we go
back to our observability use case where
you're monitoring a system you may be
looking at what is the
90th percentile of cpu utilization
across the hosts in my fleet
for this region and you can do things
such as alert if these values go above a
certain threshold or just plot these
values out on your dashboard and have a
lot of them
but also what we see um are some even
more complex analyses that you do in
real time on top of time series
databases so
some of these examples are looking at
forecasting so
being able to if you're a ride sharing
service and demand picks up in a certain
area
forecast you know how that will continue
growing or not growing and then maybe
changing the price of your service or
sending
more drivers in that area
and there are certain query types too
that are a bit more complex and time
series for time series data such as
looking at
derivatives on top of time series data
so measuring rate of change
integrals
if you're looking at maybe totals over a
period of time if you're maybe having
something like
sales per second or per day for your
ecommerce site
in your time series and want to total
per day how many cells you have you can
use that you can also use correlation
functions to compare to time series
that's useful if you're kind of looking
at trends between different similar time
series
also interpolation is another one that's
really helpful if your time series is
missing data points and you need to kind
of fill those in
so there's a lot of really
cool queries that you see done on this
time series data that i think if you're
interested in this is worth looking into
and i i think these are really powerful
queries that will also kind of will see
evolve over the next three to five years
as people are leveraging this time
series data more
i can see that's interesting so there's
a dynamic range in the data being
ingested but it sounds like you're
saying there's also this dynamic range
in queries where you might be looking at
second to second or minute to minute but
you might also be looking at trends that
last months or even years
yep that's correct yeah
great
where can listeners find out more about
you or amazon time stream
most stars can find out more about me
probably the best way would be to look
me up on linkedin
my linkedin url is just um
oddlaw.audlaw
and then i'm audrey lawrence on linkedin
also a little bit of plug if any of
these problems sound interesting to you
we are hiring um i'm hiring software
development engineers and software
development managers for my team and
there are many really exciting problems
we're working on in this space so please
thank me on linkedin if you're curious
about this
and then for time stream itself
we have public docs that detail
different use cases and different
integrations that we have
also if it's really easy to go and get
started you can
with a couple clicks in the aws console
create a database create a table and
even seed it with some data from some
sample data that we have for a couple of
different use cases and then start
playing around with queries if you want
and then there's i think on github
code samples in different languages too
if you want to directly use our apis in
any of the aws sdks
great i'll put your linkedin in the show
notes and some links to some of these
time stream resources
it was great to have you on the show
audrey this is philip winston for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening